[Music]
perhaps the most tragic thing in the
history of mankind is someone getting
their gains blocked okay right so the
answer to our question here is sometimes
sometimes not let's discuss context here
a little bit of a background before we
get started here's what we know when you
do resistance exercise and specifically
the type that's gonna elicit muscle
hypertrophy inside your muscle cells you
kick off a whole cascade of order called
signaling proteins all right and you can
see basically from the schematic these
signaling proteins that induce
hypertrophy they're known as mTOR or in
the mTOR cascade doesn't matter though
those signaling proteins core the
nucleus of the cell that holds your
genes if those are sufficient enough it
tells the DNA to replicate and induce
genes to grow more muscle tissue that's
how the quick version of a library works
on the other side when you cardio or
long duration endurance as I like to
call it or extending conditioning the
same basic cascade happens except for
these signaling proteins don't activate
muscle growth they actually activate
things like increased mitochondria or
other adaptations outer enhance
performance but it's still activating
certain molecules they go the nucleus
the nucleus then builds more proteins
but instead of building muscle proteins
they build mono Conner our endurance
proteins well I can't give you more
detail the story here later but the
quick version is there was some evidence
about 40 years ago even more
specifically in 1990s that showed the
signaling proteins that are kicked on in
this particular case one called ampk
that we've studied a lot our laboratory
actually activated another protein that
inhibits the proteins that kick on
hypertrophy so if this happens then
instead of inducing that cascade so you
did your strength training you also did
your cardio well the cardio actually
could potentially block the molecular
signals that allow hypertrophy this
your games and so the conventional
wisdom would say the hey resistance
exercise will not inhibit your endurance
adaptation so you notice the anabolic
cascade doesn't turn on a block the
endurance ones but the endurance
training can potentially inhibit the
hypertrophy it's not even necessarily
strength but I'm really specifically at
per tricking okay now that you're up to
speed what do we really know well I
actually would encourage you to check
out a recent review article by my friend
Jimmy Bagley maybe you could throw up a
picture of the article here Ryan or
Jimmy neither way but he reviewed this
really nicely I'll break down the basic
answer well here's what happens there's
a certain time cascade in which these
signaling molecules are maximized now we
don't know exactly what that is but
let's call it somewhere the neighborhood
of two to six or eight hours something
like that and for the mTOR or the
anabolic side it may be closer to that
six to eight hour window but for the
AMPK siding and dirt side it's probably
a couple of hours of s so if you were to
do these two things concurrently is what
this research is called or this type of
exercise is called in the scientific
literature you can see that the red
thing the NPK blocks the blue thing
which again black striper trophy but
since we know that it cycles back down
the NPK rather if you spread these
things out you may able to do a little
bit of both without ruining your games
so the real answer your question is
should I avoid eliminate cardio entirely
if I'm trying to hypertrophy not
necessarily it doesn't have to be your
answer it depends on a lot of situations
like how much are you doing right
certainly doing a jog jogging one lap
around the track it's not gonna block
anybody's games out the other end of the
spectrum certainly running a hundred
miles a week is gonna make it very
difficult to add muscle mass your legs
where you land in the spectrum
determines is determined on things like
well how trained are you how much are
you doing how much you trying to gain
how old are you what are your calories
look like things like that so it's
really difficult to predict we can't
make blanket statements so like if I'm
trying to hypertrophy I can't do any
cardio at all we can't make blanket
statements the other ones like well
cardio doesn't block my games and all
that's a complete myth neither one of
those are true it's a little bit
a combination so I'll take me talking
more about the physiology explain more
later in a separate video but for these
short videos I want to get straight to
your answer here's basically what I'm
gonna do
my opinion on this is number one the
best thing you can do if you're trying
to maximize hypertrophy is to reduce the
amount or number of endurance sessions
you're doing if you have to do it keep
it to once or twice per week or
eliminate it entirely that's your best
option number two that's not an option
at least reduce the volume right so less
mileage less time let's slap some pool
whatever happens to be that's not an
option number three try to perform your
endurance training on non lifting days
so we talked about that time window when
that signaling cascade is activated we
know it's gonna go back to baseline
after probably eight hours or so or more
so point being if you can separate the
two interventions the most maybe lift
Monday endurance Tuesday and kind of
cycle like that that's gonna give you
the most separation between those
signals so you'll have the least amount
of interference if that's not possible
separate your endurance training from
your resistance exercise by at least
four hours and probably do your
endurance in the morning that way say if
you did your lifting at four o'clock in
the afternoon that signal would be
allowed to peak and sell 8:00 or 9:00
o'clock the next morning which would
actually be ten twelve thirteen fourteen
hours something like that you can
maximize that I per trapeze I cause the
point don't do so much though you have a
poor training session of course and then
number five follow the appropriate
exercise order so in other words if you
have to do them in the exact same
workout so say hey I can't I don't have
the time to train twice a day do your
strength training first and your
endurance exercise at the end that way
your endurance does rule your quality of
your strength training work so again
those options are listed as best words
so that's a quick answer I don't know
how much more I need to go into this I
certainly can I've got an hour and a
half talk or something in this area I'm
not sure if I'm gonna make it though so
let me know if this is something you
want if not we call it good with the
straight answer this cardio block your
gains and kind of depends it's always a
context issue so thanks a lot for tuning
in and we'll see you next time
[Music]